(
"ai_sub_version": "3.5.2",
"generated_at": "2026-08-30T05:11:44.980963",
"lyrics_prompt_version": 9,
"subtitles_prompt_version": 18,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"any_pending": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": null,
"model_subtitles": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"model_lyrics": "google-gla:gemini-3.5-flash-lite",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true,
"max_storage_gb": 18.0
),
"search": (
"qps": 0.3,
"max_length": 4096,
"web_search_tool": "langsearch",
"timeout": 60.0,
"retries": 3,
"min_wait_seconds": 1.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 10.0,
"multiplier": 2.0
),
"validation_buffer_ms": 2000,
"verification_gap_seconds": 60,
"gap_verification_retries": 1,
"gap_verification_ignore_start": true,
"gap_verification_ignore_end": true
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": false,
"fps": 1.0,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"threshold_mb": 20,
"duration_tolerance_ms": 100,
"encoder": null
),
"start_offset_min": 0
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"lyrics": 4,
"subtitles": 4
),
"retry": (
"per_run": 5,
"max_runs": 3,
"multiplier": 2.0,
"min_wait_seconds": 30.0,
"max_wait_seconds": 300
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": true,
"scrub": false,
"progress_bars": true,
"progress_bar_width": 80,
"progress_bar_refresh_seconds": 1.0
)
生まれたてのドキドキを響かせよう
Let's make our newborn heartbeats resonate!
最高の時間 最高の仲間と
With the best time, with the best friends,
キラメキノートへ
into the glittering notebook!
今日は楽しんでってくれよ！
Have fun today, everyone!
覚えてるかな 最初の一歩
Do you remember our very first step?
たしかに私声が震えていた
My voice was definitely trembling back then.
あの時から続く未来は
The future continuing from that time
みんなと掴んだキョダイよ
is a giant dream we grasped together!
もっともっともっともっと 加速するハート
Accelerating our hearts, more and more!
一緒にいくよ どこまでも 準備はOK！
Let's go together anywhere! Are you ready?
ひらけユメの扉
Open the door of dreams!
1・2・3 キラメキライダー☆
1, 2, 3, Kirameki Rider☆!
生まれたてのドキドキを響かせよう
Let's make our newborn heartbeats resonate!
最高の時間 最高の仲間と
With the best time, with the best friends,
ここにいるよ 見つけてくれたから
I'm right here, because you found me!
君に会いたくてやってきたんだ
I came here wanting to see you,
みんなで歌おう 終わらないメロディ
let's sing an endless melody together!
キラメキまとって
Clothed in glitter,
届いてるかな 私の声
Is my voice reaching you?
届けたいのは 君に笑顔
What I want to deliver is your smile!
一歩ずつのステップで少しずつ進んで
Stepping forward one step at a time,
みんなと分かち合った
sharing it with everyone,
ぎゅっとぎゅっとぎゅっとぎゅっと
holding on tightly, tightly!
すべて抱きしめて
Embracing everything,
いこうどこまでも 準備はOK！
let's go anywhere! Are you ready?
進めキボウのその道は
Advance down that path of hope!
1・2・3 キラメキライダー☆
1, 2, 3, Kirameki Rider☆!
好きな気持ちからつくりがたしたいな
I want to shape it from feelings of love!
最高の場所 最高の仲間と
In the best place, with the best friends,
ここにいるよ まぼろしなんかじゃない
I'm right here, this is no illusion!
君の心が幸せに染まるように
So that your heart is dyed in happiness,
重なっていくハーモニー
harmonies overlapping one another,
キラメキまとって
clothed in glitter,
歌い続けたいな 踊り続けたいな
I want to keep singing, keep dancing!
生まれたてのドキドキを響かせよう
Let's make our newborn heartbeats resound
最高の時間 最高の仲間と
With the best time and best friends
キラメキに載って☆
Riding on the sparkle☆
（イェーイ！）
(Yeah!)
覚えているかな？ 最初の歌
Do you remember? My very first song
（懐かしいね）
(So nostalgic)
声が震えてた
My voice was shaking
（ほんの少し）
(Just a little bit)
あの日から続く未来は
The future continuing from that day
みんなと掴んだ今日だよ
Is today we grasped together with everyone
もっともっともっともっと加速するハート
Accelerating heart, more and more and more
（一緒に）
(Together)
行くよどこまでも
We'll go anywhere
(are you ready?)
準備は ok?
Is your preparation OK?
ひらけ！！ 夢 の トビラ を
Open up!! The door of dreams!!
(1, 2, 3)
（キラメキ ライダー☆）
Kirameki Rider☆
ここにいるよ 私 ここにいるよ
I'm right here, I am right here
君と同じ世界を見つめて
Gazing at the same world as you
キラメキライダー☆
Kirameki Rider☆
生まれたてのドキドキを響かせよう
Let's make our newborn heartbeats resound
最高の時間 最高の仲間と
With the best time and best friends
ここにいるよ 見つけてくれたから
I'm right here because you found me
君に会いたくてやってきちゃったみんなの
Everyone who came running because I wanted to see you
終わらない メロディ
Never-ending melody
キラメキに載って☆
Riding on the sparkle☆
キラメキ纏って☆
Clothed in sparkle☆
キラメキライダー☆
Kirameki Rider☆
今日は楽しんでってください！
Please enjoy today!
1周年 ありがとう！
Thank you for the 1st anniversary!
あ、皆さん、改めて、1周年を迎えちゃった、尾丸ポルカでーす！イェーイ！
Ah, everyone, once again, I'm Omaru Polka, who has reached her 1st anniversary! Yay!
どうだい1周年を迎えたポルカ、ちょっと大人になったかな？
How is it? Has Polka, reaching her 1st anniversary, grown up a little bit?
まあね、あのね、いーこいーこだね、君は本当に、いーこのみんなはね、尾丸ポルカ1周年です！いっぱいつぶやいてっちゃって！
Well, you know, good children, you guys really, everyone who's a good kid, it's #OmaruPolka1stAnniversary! Tweet lots about it!
おらおら呼んでるよ、いいね、楽しくしてまっなー！ありがとう！
Hey hey, calling you out, nice, making it fun! Thank you!
もう、すでに、うん、って感じ、やべって感じになってますかね？
Already, yeah, feeling like that, feeling like "oh no"?
いやー、だいぶね、馴染みのあるステージだって来ました、このサーカスも！あー！ありがとう！
Man, we've come to such a familiar stage, this circus too! Ah, thank you!
あのね、みんなにはね、見えないかもしれないけどね、ポルカにはね、おまえらのコメントがここにぶるって見えてるから、ぶるって見えて、おおいおいおいおい、いいねいいね、もっと書き込んじゃって書き込んじゃって！
You know, you guys might not see it, but Polka can see all your comments scrolling right here, scrolling and—hey hey hey, nice nice, type more and more!
ありがとう！
Thank you!
というわけで、まあ、えっと、今勢いでここまで来たけど、ちょっとね振り返りつつ、うーん...
So, well, um, I came this far with momentum up to now, but looking back a bit, hmm...
振り返りってあんなのね、ポルカさ、もうあの、デビューの次の日からさ、自分のこと振り返ってばっかでさ、振り返りがもうそろそろわかんなくなってきてんだよね。えーー
Looking back is a thing, you know, Polka, ever since the day after my debut, has just been looking back at myself, so I'm starting to not understand looking back anymore. Ehh—
と、あ、ポルカさ、キラメキラライダーは初めて歌ったけどさ、歌枠でいったい何曲ぐらいポルカ今まで歌ってきたんやろ1年で。あー！ありがとう！
And, oh, Polka sang "Kirameki Rider" for the first time, but how many songs has Polka sung in singing streams over this 1 year? Ah, thank you!
ずっとミュートよ、でさ、今までポルカ何曲歌ったっけさ、これ。100、100は歌ったな。えーと、1000はいってないよな、たぶん。えーと...いない？
Mute the whole time, and like, how many songs has Polka sung so far? 100, I sang 100. Um, probably hasn't reached 1,000. Um... nobody?
5億曲、あ、5億曲か！わっとりやす！
500 million songs, ah, 500 million songs! Wow, I see!
ね、200はいってるんだ。500、あ、500リアルななら、じゃ、500で提出します！500で提出し、735曲なんか？しんしん
Right, 200 is there. 500, ah, if 500 is realistic, then I'll submit 500! I'll submit 500, 735 songs or something? Shin shin—
あれだの、だ、なんか、なんか、それ、すごい、なんか、めっちゃカニングスタイルっていうか、具体的な...はい、はい、ということでね、5億兆万曲ということではい、すごい曲を歌ってきましたね！
Wait, like, something, something, that's really, like, a super cheating style, or rather, concrete... Yes, yes, so 500 trillion songs, yes, we've sung amazing songs!
1回のね、歌枠でね、めちゃ歌うよ。ただやっぱさ、ね、なんか、熱を込めてさ、歌うってなるとさ、がくがくになるね。
In a single singing stream, I sing a ton. But you know, when you put your passion into singing and all, it gets shaky.
全然すごい、ポルカキラメキでライダーできてたちゃんと。キラメキに乗ってた？
Totally amazing, Polka was doing Kirameki Rider properly. Was I riding the sparkle?
きらめきまおえてたお前らと
Shining brightly with you guys,
それだったら、いい
If that's the case, then great.
頭悪い数字だなっていうのやめてくれませんか
Would you stop calling it a stupid number?
まるでポルカが頭悪い。でも頭悪い数字を提示したのはそっちだからね？
As if Polka's stupid. But you're the ones who suggested a stupid number, right?
ポルカじゃないからね、ポルカじゃ。そっちが言ってるからね。
It's not Polka, not Polka. You guys are the ones saying it.
はい。
Yeah.
あー、よかった？あ、よかったよかった、ありがとう！ありがとう！
Ah, was that okay? Ah, good, good, thank you! Thank you!
と言うわけでね、今日はね、まあ、1年を振り返ってなどそんな可愛いこと言っておりますが
And so today, well, we're talking about looking back on our first year,
ま、実は今日はね、1年振り返り
but actually today's anniversary look-back
一周年とはなばかりの、地獄企画をね、サムネを漁想からしてね、サムネールがちょっとね、虹色で、わ、まぶしすぎて、待機所が待機できないよ、とか言ってだけど、
is just in name only—a hellish project with a rainbow thumbnail so blinding you can't even wait in the lobby.
あのー、全然ね、あの、今日は、あの、あ、海外行きもね、テンキュー、テンキュー！ノー・カオスティック！カオティックの、の、カオティック。おー！ファンタスティック、アメイジング・ライフ！ふー！
Um, not at all, um, today, um, ah, going abroad too, thank you, thank you! No chaotic! Chaotic, no, chaotic. Oh! Fantastic, amazing life! Woo!
で、即興で曲をね、あのね、作っ、ていうのをね、ずっと言ってたけど、
And I kept saying I'd improvise and make a song,
まあ、じゃあ、どうしようかな？ええと、コーナーを、変えてもらって、ええと、この1年、たくさん歌、歌いました！歌いました！
well then, what should I do? Um, let's change the corner, um, this past year, I sang lots of songs! I sang a lot!
ええ、というわけでね、せっかくなんで、ここ、ここでしか、今ここでしかやれない、ここ、そしてお前、でしかやれないことをやりたいと思います。
So since we have the chance, I want to do something that can only be done right here, right now, with you guys.
ええ、その名も一周年を歌、即興で作っちゃおぜ企画！あ、どーん！
Yes, it's called the 'Improvised 1st Anniversary Song Creation Project'! Boom!
いいですねえ。今日もBGMと、え、なんだっけ？SEと今日も上手いことマッチします。
That's nice. Today's BGM and, um, what was it, SE match up nicely again.
あ、いいですねこれなんか。
Ah, this is nice.
あ、いいねいいね。というわけでね、今日の地獄企画は、相手がいる、そう、言うこと、なんと、なんと、ナナなんと！ポルカ一人じゃ一周年で歌は作れなーい。まーす。
Ah, good, good. So today's hellish project is... there's a partner! Yes, meaning... believe it or not, Polka can't make a 1st anniversary song all by herself!
うえー！
Whoa!
というわけで、ええと、ポルカ一人じゃ難しい。もちはもちや、ほろはほろや。ほろはほろや。というわけでね、
So, um, it's hard for Polka alone. To each their own, Holo to each their own. So...
今日は、この方をお呼びしました！どうそ！
Today, we've invited this person! Here you go!
なんだよ！なんでなんだよ！そしていつもあるんだ？
Why! Why is that?! And why is there always—
そしていつもでかいんだ？
And why is it always so big?!
はーい！今日はね、なんと、ZAINくんに扮した作曲家さんの、このさんが来てくれております！イエーイ！
Hi-i! Today, Kono-san, a composer disguised as ZAIN-kun, has come to join us! Yay!
いやもうね、もう、あのZAINくんに期待するにあたってね、
Well, you know, when expecting things from ZAIN-kun...
もうね、口も取っちゃったんで今日は。
he even took off his mouth today.
多分、もともと多分この方人間だったと思うんですけど、ちょっと今日はZAINくんになっちゃったんで、もう何もものいまぬものとなってしま
He was probably human originally, but since he became ZAIN-kun today, he's become someone who doesn't speak...
ちょ、キーボード、座れる？大丈夫？あ、よかったよかった。
Hey, can you sit at the keyboard? You okay? Oh, good, good.
え、じゃあなんかさ、ほら、なんかさ、ほら、せっかくだし、あ、そのちっちゃいおててでさ、ほらね、こまおさん？あ、よかった！いる！いる、おめでとう！今日のスペシャルゲストでございます！
Well then, hey, since we have the chance, with those tiny hands, Kono-san? Ah, great! He's here! He's here, congratulations! Today's special guest!
みんなはこのさんのことは知っているかなあ？知っているかなあ？
I wonder if everyone knows about Kono-san? Do you know him?
なんかぴってして。
Just do a little salute like this.
お、いいね！なんかアイスがあるぞ、やりやすさすぎ！いいな！
Oh, nice! There's some ice cream, so easy to do! Nice!
え、というわけでね、あのね、まあ一発で分かるで言えばポルカの枠でスーパーチャットとか読んでいる時だともう分かりやすいのかなっていう曲が1個あるよね？
So, um, if you want a song that's instantly recognizable, there's one from when Polka reads Super Chats on stream, right?
お、じゃ！
Oh, here we go!
スーパーチャットありがとう、とっても嬉しいよ
Super Chat, thank you so much, I'm so happy!
って入れてれてれててスーパーチャットありがとう
Putting that in, Super Chat, thank you!
今日は一周年スーパーチャットが今目に、入ってないけどありがとう
Today is the 1st anniversary, Super Chats aren't in my eyes right now, but thank you!
それさ、あの、あの君の采配で決まるじゃん？ねえ。
That depends on your call, right? Hey.
ちゃんじゃないんだよ。
It's not 'chan'.
あの、終わらないかと思った一瞬、永遠に、あのいつもの配信のように、と思ってき
I thought it would never end, for eternity, like my usual streams...
あ、BGMありがとうございますね、帰ってきてくれてね。ちょっと一周年エンドレス、エンドレススーパーチャットのソングが流れるかもしれないじゃん。
Ah, thank you for the BGM, for coming back. An endless 1st anniversary Super Chat song might play.
ポルカがさ、今コメント読んだ瞬間に、あの、スパチャが途切れたからどうしようかと思った。
Polka thought, right when I read the comment, the Super Chat stopped, so what should I do?
あ、大丈夫です。あのね、こうやってね、あの促してるわけではないです。こういう曲を作ってくださっているZAINくんなんですよって。
Ah, it's fine. You know, I'm not prompting you like this. It's ZAIN-kun who made this kind of song for us!
やもうね、ほら、いっぱい拍手して。
Oh, look, give a big round of applause.
拍手してて可愛いね。ねえ、もうこんななっちゃってね、こんな、こんななっちゃってね、
Clapping, how cute. Hey, he ended up like this...
頑張って今日は引いてくれるそうなんですが。まあ、今日は、一周年。
He's gonna do his best to play today, but well, today's the 1st anniversary.
ルっさいよ！ 1周年の歌、
Shut up! A 1st anniversary song...
あの、完全アドリブなんだけど、
Um, it's completely improvised though.
一応さ、ほら、来てもらって、
I mean, look, I had you come here,
でももう口がないからさ、
but you don't have a mouth, so...
できると思う？
Do you think you can do it?
おっ！できるって言ってる！
Oh! You said you can!
すごいすごいすごい！
Amazing, amazing!
いけそうな気がするね、これね！
I feel like we can do this!
ポルカが頑張るっていうよりか、こっさん頑張ってって感じだけど
Instead of Polka trying hard, it's more like Kossan's working hard.
じゃあ、まあ、テーマから決めるのがいいのかな、こういうのって。
Well, I guess we should start with a theme.
どういうところから決めていこうっか？
Where should we start deciding?
何がいいのかな？
What would be good?
やっぱ、でも、歌詞はコメントとポルカとやっていきたいし、
I want to work on the lyrics with the chat,
曲はなんとなくさ、うーん……
and the song is sort of... um...
なんかさ、じゃあ、テーマをください、何か。
So, give me a theme, anything.
なんかあるかな？
Is there anything?
嘘やん！
No way!
これあれじゃん、崖の上やん、もう。
This is already on top of a cliff, you know.
ジャークやん、これ！
That's a jerk move!
いや！いや！違うぞ！
No! No! That's wrong!
あの女が悪かったのよ！
That woman was in the wrong!
あたしじゃない！あたしじゃない！
It wasn't me! It wasn't me!
もうやだ、あたしここ嫌い！
No more, I hate this place!
「待て」
"Wait."
君がそこで命を落として、誰が救われるというんだい？
Who would be saved if you lose your life there?
でも、君がそこで命を落としたところで何も変わらない、
But even if you lose your life there, nothing changes,
世界は変わらない、明日ばっ……
the world won't change, tomorrow is...
あっ、大丈夫です。もう一回やって、今の。
Ah, it's fine. Do that part again.
これがテーマか……
Is this the theme...
これ1周年の歌かな……
Is this a 1st anniversary song...
どうして？どうして？
Why? Why?
今は、たぶんこれを読みながら、ポルカはいい感じの歌詞探しとくから、
For now, I'll read this and look for good lyrics,
コメントは歌詞を打って！はい！いいね！よ、よ、
so chat, type out some lyrics! Yes! Good!
もうフリースタイルはしちゃいながらこのままだぞ！
We're doing freestyle like this!
誰かいい感じのテーマをください。
Someone give me a good theme.
カブトムシ、カブトムシが怖いんだ。
Rhinoceros beetles, I'm scared of rhinoceros beetles.
なんか、強そうじゃない？ロックっぽくない？
Doesn't it sound strong? Isn't it rock-like?
あっ、いいね！
Ah, nice!
なんかもうちょっとテンポ早いか？
Should the tempo be a bit faster?
カブトムシが怖いんだぁ！
I'm scared of rhinoceros beetles!
カブトムシ、カブトムシ、カブトムシが怖いんだ！どうして、どうしてカブトムシはあんなに怖いんだ！
Rhinoceros beetles, I'm so scared of them! Why are they so scary?!
なんでカブトムシはあんなに怖いんだけど、クワガタは……かっこいい！
Why are rhinoceros beetles so scary, but stag beetles are... cool!
1周年の歌ちゃうやん！
This isn't a 1st anniversary song at all!
1周年の歌じゃないじゃん、なんか。
It's not a 1st anniversary song.
もっとさ、なんか、いい感じの歌詞、歌詞の案をください。
Give me some better lyric ideas.
まあ、とりあえず「おめでとう」っていうことと、あと、メジャー路線行こう！
Well, first "congratulations", and let's go mainstream!
おめでと……いいね、いいね！その思考中の音、いいね！
Congrat- ...Nice, nice! That thinking sound is good!
なんか、あの……えーっと、なんか「おめでとう」感じの曲じゃん？
Um, it's a "congratulatory" kind of song, right?
えーっと、1周年、ポルカは頑張ってきました。
Uh, for the 1st anniversary, Polka has worked hard.
頑張りを体現できるような歌。低気圧に勝った感じ。
A song embodying that hard work. Like beating low pressure.
あっ、いいね！低気圧に勝った感じ？
Ah, nice! Beating low pressure?
低気圧に勝ってポルカが1年輝き……なんだろう、アメージングでグレースな感じのさ、
Defeating low pressure and shining for a year... amazing and graceful,
ついに生まれたよ！ポルカは去年この日にホロライブに入り、低気圧に勝った！低気圧に勝った！
She was finally born! Polka joined Hololive last year on this day and beat low pressure!
そして、明日からは高気圧になるよ！高気圧って素晴らしい！
And starting tomorrow, it will be high pressure! High pressure is wonderful!
これが1周年おめでとう歌よ！
This is the 1st anniversary congratulations song!
1周年ありがとう！
Thank you for the 1st anniversary!
あれ? できてない? これ?
Huh? Isn't this done yet?
あれ? 完成したのか?
Huh? Is it finished?
ちょっと待って。あれ? 完成した? あれ?
Wait a minute. Huh? Is it finished? Huh?
ん? 完成したか今の?
Hmm? Was that finished just now?
あ、完成した! やった! やった!
Ah, it's done! Yay! Yay!
完成したっぽくない?
Doesn't it look finished?
あれ? でもこういう感じなのかな?
Huh? But is this how it's supposed to be?
あれ? なんか、でもこういうか、なんかさ、打ち合わせのキーボードとさ、ちょっとなんかまた変わってきてない?
Huh? Wait, but like this, or rather, y'know, isn't it a bit different from the keyboard in our meeting?
なんか、ワンチャン
Like, maybe...
ちょっと、あの、やらせしようぜみたいなこともしたのよね。なんか
We also talked about doing something like, y'know, staging it. Like...
やらせしようぜって、言うのはあれだけど、やらせし、あ、いやいや、やらせなしです、
Saying "let's stage it" is one thing, no, no, no staging,
あ、やらせしてません、してません、してません、してません!
ah, I didn't stage it, I didn't, I didn't, I didn't!
ちょ、なんか、あれ? なんか結構
Wait, like, huh? It's kind of...
でも、ま、これは結構新顔が見えていい感じだよね。
Still, well, this is pretty good seeing a new face.
高気圧になったよっていう。高気圧になって
Like, it became a high-pressure system. Becoming a high-pressure system
えー、虹がかかって、えー、なんて言うんだろ、なんか最後うまく決めたいよな、
Uh, a rainbow appears, uh, how should I put it, I wanna nail the ending well,
それだ。今の感じで行くんだとしたら。
that's it. If we're going with this vibe.
サーカスカンが欲しい! 確かにな!
I want that circus feel! True!
忘れていたこのサーカス店のと、サーカス感! 忘れておりました、ポルカは。
I forgot about this circus tent and circus vibe! Polka forgot.
こう、だからサーカステントにいた小さい尾丸ポルカが旅立ち、低気圧というところから、えーっと、バーンと言って、高気圧の素晴らしい虹がかかったとかは? えー? だめか。
So, the little Omaru Polka who was in the circus tent sets off, from a low-pressure area, uh, goes "bam!", and a wonderful high-pressure rainbow appears, how about that? Huh? No good?
なんか、あ、空中ブランコに音源さしゅうピュ-ンって感じ、なんかカートゥーンミュージックっぽい感じ? ああ、難しそうだな、なんか。
Like, oh, audio on a flying trapeze going pyuun, like cartoon music? Ah, sounds difficult, somehow.
ああ、なんかしょ、なんか、かぶとむしはもう忘れろや! いつまで引っ張っとんねん!
Ah, sort of, like, forget about the rhinoceros beetle! How long are you gonna drag this out!
かぶとむしの曲出てこないよ、ポルカは。うん、気圧に負けない。
A rhinoceros beetle song isn't coming out, Polka. Yeah, I won't lose to air pressure.
もじゃあ気圧とかそういうのどうでもいいから、あれ? おめでたい感じからどっか行った?
Well then, air pressure and stuff doesn't matter, so, hmm, huh? Did it stray from the celebratory vibe?
ええー! サーカスで、1周年で、こんなにポルカ成長しました! なんか
Eee! At the circus, for our 1st anniversary, Polka has grown this much! Like
えー、なんか、でも、かわいさねがいいな、ちょっと、うーん、ロック?
Uh, like, but, cuteness is nice, a bit, hmm, rock?
なんか、戦隊ものとかそういうジャジャーン! ジャジャジャジャジャジャーン!
Like, Super Sentai stuff or something like jajaan! Jajajajaja jajaan!
さあ、尾丸ポルカ、2年目に入りました、尾丸ポルカ。
Now, Omaru Polka, has entered her 2nd year, Omaru Polka.
さあ、これからどんな戦いを見せ、戦い、戦い誰と戦うんだ一体、戦いを見せていくのか、いいですね、これは何かの何かが雇われていくんでしょ。
Now, what kind of battles will she show, battles, battles, who is she fighting anyway, will she show battles, nice, something or other is getting hired here.
いつ歌に入りますか? この曲はいつ歌に入りますか?
When does the singing start? When does the singing in this song start?
ぬわーっ、だ、だ、だ、だ、ポルカの1年!
Nwaa-, da, da, da, da, Polka's first year!
ポルカの1年
Polka's first year
最初は色々こともあり
At first, there were various things
低気圧があって
There was low pressure
はもいたかった はもいたかったけど 虹色のサムネイルもありました
I wanted to harmonize, I wanted to harmonize, but there were also rainbow-colored thumbnails
ここがロックにいこ だけど
Here, let's go rock, but...
だけど ポルカは強くなったよ 今日は素晴らしい尾丸ポルカいっすれ はっすたぐ おまるぽるかいっすれんで つぶやいてくれよ!
But Polka has gotten stronger! Today is a wonderful Omaru Polka, tweet it out with the hashtag Omaru Polka!
はっすたぐ おまるぽるかいっすれんで つぶやいてくれよ!
Tweet it out with the hashtag Omaru Polka!
これで行く、ど、いろいろあん出ましたけど、どういう方向性でいっ、一番いくのが楽しいのかな?
How should we go about this? We've come up with various ideas, but what direction would be the most fun to go in?
なんか、メロディーはいいのにって言われ、ん、ポルカがだめみたいに言うじゃん。
Like, they say 'the melody is good, though', implying Polka is no good.
あ、親しみより元気。でも狂気が足りないって言ってる人がいて、狂気って何? 狂気って何だよ!
Ah, friendliness over energy. But some people say there's a lack of madness. What is madness? What is madness?!
だいぶ狂気だろ、この企画。
This project is pretty mad already.
な、ほらもう埋まっちゃったじゃん、どうすんの? 嫌になっちゃったじゃん。買いたくなっちゃってるじゃんこれ。
See, it's already filled up, what are we gonna do? It's getting annoying. You're making me want to buy this.
入れとげてよ、もう！
Put it in for me, come on!
シシロちゃん、入れてあげて！
Shishiro-chan, put it in for her!
えー、入れたくないの？
Eh, you don't want to put it in?
じゃあラミィちゃんほら、最後入れてあげて！
Then Lamy-chan, look, put it in at the end!
ポチッ…
Click...
違うんだって。仮想大賞やってる場合じゃないの。
That's not it. This isn't the time to do a comedy contest.
あの…ポルカが、いい、いい相手を見つけてしまっちゃったからさ、
Uhm... Polka found such a good, good partner,
もう永遠これができるんだよ。とりあえず、まあ…
so she can do this forever. For now, well...
固まってるようで固まらないし、
It looks like it's freezing, but it doesn't freeze,
ポルカって何でもできちゃうんだなっていうのが分かってきましたね、だいぶ。
and I've come to realize Polka can do anything, pretty much.
きらめきジェットコースター…って、きらめきジェットコースター？
Kirameki Jet Coaster... wait, Kirameki Jet Coaster?
キラキラしてて、あ、分かった！めっちゃ落ち込んでるところから急にガーンて上げたらどうなるの？
Sparkling... ah, I get it! What happens if you suddenly boost it up from when you're super depressed?
なんかさ、きらめきジェットコースターだよ、きらめきジェットコースター。
Like, "Kirameki Jet Coaster", "Kirameki Jet Coaster".
こう、やばいなんか、
Like, oh no, like
最初のね、新歌詞がね、最初の新しくした歌詞が、えっと…うん、きらめき、空中ブランコ、感情のジェットコースター
The first, new lyrics, the new lyrics at the start, uh... um, sparkling, trapeze, rollercoaster of emotions
えっと、感情のジェットコースター、最初だから、遅刻して落ち込んだみたいな、が、なるほどね、えっと
Uhm, rollercoaster of emotions, since it's the start, like being late and feeling down, like, I see, uh...
ポルカはひとり、ポルカはひとり、ポルカはひとり、
Polka is alone, Polka is alone, Polka is alone,
一人で、一人で、進んでいく。
alone, alone, moving forward.
でもそこには、でもたどり着いた先にはみんながいて、
But there, but at the destination she reached, everyone is there,
高気圧になって、虹がかかって、
becoming high pressure, a rainbow appearing,
おお、いいじゃん！なんかいいじゃん！
Oh, that's good! That's kind of good!
あ、これ今沈んでるところ？沈んでるところ。あ、まだ沈んでて、で、まだジェットコースターの下な、うーん、うーん、
Ah, is this sinking right now? Sinking. Ah, still sinking, and still at the bottom of the roller coaster, um, um,
うん、で、でも、みんながいた！みんながいた！みんながいた！サーカスがやれた！
Um, and, but, everyone was there! Everyone was there! Everyone was there! Circus was able to happen!
な、な、仲間がいるよ、もう過ちはおかさない！
Friends are here, I won't make mistakes anymore!
なんとかかんとかも、突き進んでいくよー！
Somehow or other, pushing forward!
ここだね！あ、いーじゃん！ここめっちゃいい！いーじゃん！いーじゃん！いや、いーじゃんここ！
Here it is! Ah, that's good! This place is super good! Good! Good! No, this place is good!
仲間たちに出会えた！やったー！
Met my comrades! Yay!
やった！やっぱりポルカが一番！ポルカおるよ、ポルカおるよっていうのが欲しいのか。
Yay! As expected, Polka is number one! "Polka is here, Polka is here", is that what you want?
ポルカおるよ！ポルカおるか！ポルカおるか！ポルカおるよー！
Polka is here! Is Polka here? Is Polka here? Polka is hereee!
仲間たち、夢希望…
Comrades, dreams, hopes...
いいね、そこらへんかな？
Nice, around there, huh?
で、おっ、落ち込んでるところは多分低気圧だから、そこから多分虹やなんかが挿してきて
And, oh, the place where she's depressed is probably low pressure, so from there probably a rainbow and stuff shines in,
あ、いいね。とりあえず感情ジェットコースターはいんしゃ、感情…でもなんかちょっと待って、
Ah, nice. For now, emotional roller coaster is in, emotion... but wait a bit,
きらめきライダーパクリたいから、感情きらめきジェットコースターとかにしよっか？
since I want to rip off "Kirameki Rider", let's make it "Emotion Kirameki Jet Coaster"?
光、あ、光、いいね。光ジェットコースターは2周目。あ、かっこいい！それ何それ！めっちゃいいじゃん！
Light, ah, light, nice. Light jet coaster is the second round. Ah, cool! What is that! That's super good!
ジェットコースターは2周目、虹、サーカス、空中ブランコ、えー、えーと、無限、無限！いいね無限。なんか光の先へ、とかそういう、あ、いーじゃん！いーじゃん！
Jet coaster second round, rainbow, circus, trapeze, um, um, infinite, infinite! Nice, infinite. Like, towards the light, or something like that, ah, that's good! That's good!
あ、で、最後、最後なんか夕暮れが、なんかこう、夕暮れの感じで終わっていこう。
Ah, and, last, last, like twilight, like this, with a twilight feel let's end.
よし。多分最初はめっちゃ暗いところからいきなりガーンてやっておたびでめっちゃきらーってしてそのままでピャーンてしてって感じね。
Alright. Probably start from a super dark place and suddenly bang with a war cry and sparkle intensely and just pyan- like that.
サビ！サビはだからさっきのは、えーと、さっきのサビ何だっけ？もう一回お願いします！
Chorus! The chorus is, so the previous one is, uh, what was the previous chorus? One more time please!
あ、そうそうこれこれ！タンタンタタタンタタタタタン... あ、描き出す虹のアーチ、描き出す虹のアーチ、
Ah, yes yes, this this! Tan tan tata tan tata ta tan... Ah, drawing a rainbow arch, drawing a rainbow arch,
でもここで君に会えたよ！でもここで君に会えたよ！やっと君に会えたよ！描き出す虹のアーチ！
But I met you here! But I met you here! I finally met you here! Drawing a rainbow arch!
カブトムシは忘れなよ！
Don't forget the rhinoceros beetle!
あの、始まちゃったそうなので
Um, it seems like we've already started, so...
えっと、あの、ちょっと本格的に今、あの、たぶん
Um, right now, um, Zaln-kun is probably...
がんばってます、ざいんくんちょっと。
trying really hard right now, um.
今、ちょっとね、一応マジのガチで作ってるから、ちょっとあの、あと歌詞コメントもまとめといてください。
Right now, since we're making it for real, um, please also summarize the lyric comments later.
はい、歌詞ね、今出た歌詞ね、ちょっとまとめといてもらって、ポルカちょっと、あの、こんさんのね休憩を休憩してねえんだけどさ、今も、あの、ポルカ
Yes, the lyrics, the lyrics that just came out, please summarize them, and Polka, um, Konda-san's break-- taking a break, but even now, um, Polka...
の一応1周年なのでね、ちょっと、ポルカも歌って、歌って、歌っていいですかー？
since it's my 1st anniversary, um, can Polka also sing, sing, can I sing?
歌いまーす、何も言わせずとも！
I'll sing! Without letting you say a word!
ねぇねぇ、こんさんなんかいい感じの医療やってくれよ！
Hey hey, Kon-san, do some cool-looking medical stuff!
かっこいい感じのさあ、でっせーい！俺も歌いたいんだあ！
A cool kind of—Desseiy! I want to sing too!
違う違う違う、ちょっとごめんごめん、ちょっと乗っちゃったんだけど。
Wait wait wait, sorry sorry, I got a bit carried away there.
あの、実烈はね、持ってきた曲、ちょっとセクシー寄りなんだよ、こんさん。セクシー寄りなんだよ。
Um, actually, the song I brought is a bit on the sexy side, Kon-san. It's on the sexy side.
なんか、ちょっとセクシー寄りの入ってないかな、逆に。
Like, isn't there a sexy-leaning entrance, conversely?
いや、それはだって、え？いいの？え？いいの？
No, because, eh? Is it okay? Eh? Is it okay?
嗤々、臨界実験に付き合う朝
Ah, in the morning of the critical experiment,
14封を嘲る蔑床
The contemptuous bed sneers at the 14 pounds.
「如何仕そうもないけれど」
"Though there's nothing we can do about it,"
気が狂うヒトの振りをしているキミを観ている
I am watching you pretending to be out of your mind.
嗤々、面倒だったから切り捨てた
Ah, because it was troublesome, I discarded it.
4U型を掬う烙句
The rack snatches the 4U size.
「申し訳ないけれど」
"Though I am terribly sorry,"
擦れ違うモノに無為に期待を背負わせている
I'm making things that pass by uselessly carry my expectations.
夜更かしはイドの暴走
"Staying up late is the rampage of the id,"
目に焼き付いた青の感光
"The blue sensitization seared into my eyes,"
モラトリアム的人生
"A moratorium-like life,"
最大公約数緩衝材
"The greatest common divisor as a buffer."
食べてすぐ寝て醜になる
If you sleep right after eating, you become an ox.
起きてまた寝て人でない?
Wake up and sleep again, are you a monster?
「失敗!」
"Fail!"
急転 相まって壊したってDEAD強行!
Sudden turns, breaking it together, forcing a DEAD!
「なんてこった!死んでしまう!」
"Oh my god, I'm going to die!"
だがツマミは回る雁字搦MATE!
Yet the knob turns, bound tightly, MATE!
同位体 終いには取り戻したい!って
Isotope, in the end, I want to take it back!
「間無地獄へ堕ちる!堕ちる!」
"Falling down into endless hell! Falling!"
だが眩むunbalance 遥か遠くへ
Yet the blinding unbalance leads far away.
マキシマイザー マキシマイザー
Maximizer, Maximizer,
Maximizer, Maximizer.
嗤々、息を吹き返す朝
Ah, returning to life in the morning,
14封を嘲る蔑床
The contemptuous bed sneers at the 14 pounds.
「如何仕そうもないね」
"Though there's nothing we can do,"
気が狂うヒトの振りをしているキミに言う
I say to you pretending to be out of your mind.
「簡単な言葉それだけを信じたいなら」
"If you want to believe in simple words alone,"
「物足りないよ」
"It's not enough."
「心から申し訳ないならする事あるでしょ」
"If you're truly sorry, there's something you should do."
キミにとって同じに聴こえる音に答え見出す気もない
You have no intention of finding answers in sounds that sound the same to you.
後悔でひびくエゴ
Ego rampant with regret,
目に焼き付いた青の感光
The blue sensitization seared into my eyes.
モラトリアム的人生
A moratorium-like life,
液晶ディスプレイは断頭台
The liquid crystal display is a guillotine.
食べてすぐ寝て醜になる
If you sleep right after eating, you become an ox.
起きてまた寝て人でない?
Wake up and sleep again, are you a monster?
「降参するよ、マキシマイザー」
"I surrender, Maximizer."
意志のため燃え上がらせた愛が殺人になる
The love ignited for the sake of will turns into murder.
「なんてこった!生きてしまう!」
"Oh my god, I'm going to live!"
だが怒用に手掴まれて再び一緒に地獄行き
Yet grabbed by the hand of fury, we head to hell together once more.
「失敗!」
"Fail!"
急転 相まって壊したってDEAD強行!
Sudden turns, breaking it together, forcing a DEAD!
「なんてこった!死んでしまう!」
"Oh my god, I'm going to die!"
だがツマミは回る雁字搦MATE!
Yet the knob turns, bound tightly, MATE!
同位体 終いには取り戻したい!って
Isotope, in the end, I want to take it back!
「間無地獄へ堕ちる!堕ちる!」
"Falling down into endless hell! Falling!"
だが眩むunbalance 遥か遠くへ
Yet the blinding unbalance leads far away.
マキシマイザー マキシマイザー
Maximizer, Maximizer,
Maximizer, Maximizer.
ああ、あり得ない程至近な距離
Ah, such an unimaginably close distance,
舞うの? 抜ける至近な距離
Are you dancing? Breaking away at close range.
あの、いいの? 至近な距離
Um, is it okay? At close range.
あのさ、右脳に効く秘密
You know, a secret that works on the right brain.
ほら、あり得ない程至近な距離
Look, such an unimaginably close distance,
唯一無二のジョーカー手にするためり
To get your hands on the one and only joker,
欲望もさらけ出してる
I'm laying bare my desires too.
ほっと離れていく世界の一路気も
The logic of the world drifting further away,
キミは楽しめるかな
I wonder if you can enjoy it.
重要なのは
What's important is
全て知ってあと戻りはできないステージへ
heading to a stage of no return after knowing everything.
君は楽しめるかな
I wonder if you can enjoy it.
悪戯に君をずっと見ていた訳じゃない
It's not like I've been watching you playfully all this time.
僕の考えを当ててごらんよ
Try guessing what I'm thinking.
些細な仕草 視線 瞬き
Subtle gestures, gazes, blinks—
君はもう掌に
you're already in the palm of my hand.
剥ぎ出しのtrapなんてかかる訳ないわ
There's no way you'd fall for a trap like that.
甘い言葉にも惑わされない
You won't be swayed by sweet words either.
心の奥の奥の奥まで見透かしてしまうよ
I can see right through to the very depths of your heart.
looking thinking touching feeling
why you know?
i know it
looking thinking touching feeling
understand?
meaning, meaning of love
are you ready?
自覚ないでしょう思い通りに 君は動かされている事！
You don't even realize you're being made to move as planned!
単純じゃないの仕掛けのhintを 全て見落とさないで
Don't overlook any of the hints in this complex setup.
meaning of love, meaning of love
加速してく
Accelerating—
二人の鼓動
our two heartbeats.
なんかうまく歌えませんでした！サスペクト！
Somehow I couldn't sing it well! "Suspect"!
ありがとうございます！
Thank you very much!
先輩コーラスありがとうございます！
Senior chorus, thank you very much!
この曲めっちゃ好き！すげえ練習しました！
I love this song so much! I practiced it so much!
ああ、歌枠でもたぶん歌った......
Ah, I probably sang it in a singing stream too...
練習してる、すげえ練習した曲と練習がーあまりできていない曲の、あれが顕著に出ている、出ている。
You can really tell the difference between songs I practiced a ton and songs I didn't.
どうだい？どうだい君、よかった？よかった？
How was it, you guys? Was it good? Was it good?
サスペクトしてた？さすさすしてたねみんな。さすさすしとるね、おー！
Were you being "sus"? You guys were being sus. You're being sus, oh!
いやあ、ちょっと待って。大丈夫。
Man, hold on. It's okay.
今頑張って多分ね、あの作ってると思うから。ちょっとね、ふう。
Right now they're probably working hard to make it. So, phew.
頑張った！先輩ありがとー！
I did my best! Senior, thank you!
ちょっとね、このままね、次の曲も実はあるんです。
Actually, there's a next song coming right up, too.
ちょっと水飲むわ。
Let me drink some water.
ざいんくんよろしく。
Za-in-kun, if you please.
おいし、ありがとうざいんくん
Delicious, thank you, Za-in-kun.
はい、ただいま。ただいまー。
Yep, I'm back. Welcome back—I mean, I'm back.
あ、おかえりって言ってくれてる！すごいすごいすごい！意思の疎通が図れた！
Ah, you're saying "welcome back"! Amazing, amazing! We achieved mutual understanding!
というわけで、えっと次の曲歌いたいですが、えっとこれは......うーん、いや言っとけよって話なんだけど。
And so, um, I'd like to sing the next song, but, um... well, you could say "just tell us already."
えっと、ま、この曲を一人で歌うのは最後にしよう、したいなと思っている曲です。
Well, this is a song I wanted to make the last one I'd sing by myself.
なぜむしろ逆に、ここに来るまでのこのね、えっと「ねぽらぼ一緒ね」って書いてある、このね、人たちはね、歌っていないのだろうかっていうのがね、ちょっとね、あの不思議なぐらいなんですけど、いろんな理由とかいろんなことが想定されたりとかして、4人で歌うことががかなわなかったんだけど、ポルカは一人で今日は最後歌ってやるぜこれを、っていう曲で。
Why didn't the people written here as "Nepolabo together" sing it? It's a mystery—various reasons and circumstances were imagined, and we couldn't sing it together as four, but Polka decided, "Today I'm going to sing this all by myself as the finale!"
いきます！ありがとう！そう！そう！
Here we go! Thank you! That's right! That's right!
そう、ナイスもう一回って？
Nice, "one more time"?
お？その手拍子はなんこかい？いいね、3つなんだね！
Oh? How many claps was that? Nice, it's three!
わかった、3つらしいです手拍子は。
Understood, apparently it's three claps.
そう、必要なのは手だけで大丈夫！いくよ？
That's right, all you need is your hands, it's fine! Ready?
じゃあ、歌わせてくださーい！
Well then, please let me sing!
BLUE CLAPPER！
BLUE CLAPPER!
手を上げて clap your hands 海の向こうまで
Raise your hands, clap your hands, all the way across the sea.
clap your hands 音の響きよ 手を叩こう 手を叩こう
Clap your hands, let the sound resonate and clap your hands, clap your hands!
ほら一緒にさぁ everybody
Look, everyone together, everybody!
clap your hands 空の向こうまで
Clap your hands, all the way across the sky,
clap your hands 響きますように
Clap your hands, so that it echoes far.
手を叩こう 手を叩こう
Clap your hands, clap your hands!
光射す ぼくたちの未来
The future of us illuminated by light—
5 4 3 2 1
始めようか さあ diving
Let's begin, come on, diving.
待っても意味ない timing
Timing where waiting has no meaning.
あの魚みたいに swimming swimming
Swimming, swimming like that fish.
引き寄せるの lighting
Lighting that pulls you in.
まだ見えないよね maybe
Still invisible, maybe?
この先には何があるの？
What lies ahead of this?
まだ早いよ take it
Still too early, take it.
追い付くまでする shaking
Shaking until we catch up.
でもたまには止まって thinking thinking
But sometimes stop and think, think.
変えてみせるの change
Change it to show what we can do.
ふみだすのさ stepping
Stepping forward.
掴んでみせるよ キラキラ my dream
Grasping my sparkling dream.
かなう日まで story 繋ぐから
Connecting the story until the day it comes true,
だって君にずっと見ていてほしいから
because I want you to keep watching me forever.
手を上げて clap your hands 海の向こうまで
Raise your hands, clap your hands, all the way across the sea.
clap your hands 音の響きよ 手を叩こう 手を叩こう
Clap your hands, let the sound resonate and clap your hands, clap your hands!
ほら一緒にさぁ everybody
Look, everyone together, everybody!
clap your hands 空の向こうまで
Clap your hands, all the way across the sky,
clap your hands 響きますように
Clap your hands, so that it echoes far.
手を叩こう 手を叩こう
Clap your hands, clap your hands!
重なる wave 世界を揺らし
Overlapping waves shake the world.
終わりがある事くらい既に i know
I already know that everything has an end,
でもまだまだ泳ぎ足りないの
but I still haven't had enough of swimming.
give me crazy
まるで lazy?
like lazy?
次元混ざり合うの
Dimensions mingling together,
すべて塗り替える blue
painting everything blue.
手を上げて clap your hands 海の向こうまで
Raise your hands, clap your hands, all the way across the sea.
clap your hands 音の響きよ 手を叩こう 手を叩こう
Clap your hands, let the sound resonate and clap your hands, clap your hands!
ほら一緒にさぁ everybody
Look, everyone together, everybody!
clap your hands 空の向こうまで
Clap your hands, all the way across the sky,
clap your hands 響きますように
Clap your hands, so that it echoes far.
手を叩こう 手を叩こう
Clap your hands, clap your hands!
光射す ぼくたちの未来
The future of us illuminated by light—
Oh yeah!
金杯手拍子してください！
Please clap your hands in rhythm!
今日はいらないプライド
Today we don't need pride,
見せかけは捨てて
throw away the pretense.
何時にでも一緒しようよ
Let's be together anytime,
君は何を日々
what do you spend your days on?
ときめかせてSPARKING
Make it spark, SPARKING!
暗闇に放つレッドアミューズメント
Unleash a red amusement into the darkness!
光らせてステージ作るから
Making the stage shine,
さぁ君にもっと見てほしいから
Come on, because I want you to watch me even more!
手を上げて clap your hands!
Raise your hands, clap your hands!
空の向こうまで clap your hands!
Up to the other side of the sky, clap your hands!
ときめき増すように手を叩こう
Let's clap our hands to increase the excitement,
手を叩こう！
clap your hands!
ほら一緒にさあ
Come on, let's do it together,
Everybody clap your hands!
空の向こうまで clap your hands!
Up to the other side of the sky, clap your hands!
ときめき増すように手を叩こう
Let's clap our hands to increase the excitement,
手を叩こう！
clap your hands!
華麗なるweb 世界を揺らせ
Magnificent web, shake the world!
一人よりが二人
More than being alone, two people,
奥深い恋だって知り合うの
getting to know a deep love,
でもまだまだ泳ぎ足りないの
but we still haven't swum enough,
秘密だらけリゾート
a resort full of secrets!
君もフェクシー
You're fancy too!
次元が混ざり合う全て塗り替えるブルーストーリー
A blue story where dimensions mix and repaint everything!
手を上げて clap your hands!
Raise your hands, clap your hands!
空の向こうまで clap your hands!
Up to the other side of the sky, clap your hands!
ときめき増すように手を叩こう
Let's clap our hands to increase the excitement,
手を叩こう！
clap your hands!
ほら一緒にさあ
Come on, let's do it together,
Everybody clap your hands!
空の向こうまで clap your hands!
Up to the other side of the sky, clap your hands!
ときめき増すように手を叩こう
Let's clap our hands to increase the excitement,
手を叩こう！
clap your hands!
光り輝く僕たちの未来
Our shining future,
最高にしようよ！
let's make it the best!
ありがとう！
Thank you!
ありがとうございましたー！
Thank you very much!
めっちゃ手叩いてくれてた！
You guys were clapping your hands so much!
ありがとう！
Thank you!
1人で歌うの...これがステージで歌うのはさ、最初に最後がいいな。
Singing alone... I thought starting or ending with it would be nice.
次は4人で立ってるようにポルカめちゃ頑張るから！
Polka will work really hard so next time we can stand here as four!
っていうのをいま、えっと、他のメンバーに言ってます。
I'm telling the other members that right now.
よし！よかった！ありがとう！
Alright! I'm glad! Thank you!
ポルカのお歌のターンはここまでとなっております。
Polka's singing turn ends here.
あとは、そう、
And then, yeah,
くんのさん、作詞曲だよ。
Kuno-san, it's your composition and lyrics.
やるよ、続き。
We'll do the rest.
え、ポルカ頭待って待って
Eh, Polka, wait, wait, wait!
え、なにそれちょっと待って！
Eh, what is that, wait a minute!
えっ、待って待って待って待って待って！えっ、なにこれちょっと待って！
Eh, wait wait wait! Eh, what is this, wait!
え、はあ？た、た、た、た、た、た、たららら、た、た、た、た、た、た、
Eh, huh? Ta ta ta ta...
え？なに？ちょっと待って？え？え？これさっきの続きじゃん？
Eh? What? Wait a minute? Isn't this the continuation of earlier?
た、た、た、た、た、た、
Ta ta ta ta...
え、なにこれ？なに？なんてできたのこれ？
Eh, what is this? How did this get made?
え？え？え？
Eh? Eh? Eh?
ちょっと、あの、え、え、できあがっとるやないかい！
Wait, it's already finished, isn't it?!
あの、その過程、あー、過程はもうさっきの裏でバチバチやってたのか、あれが過程やったんか。
The process was us going back and forth backstage earlier, was that it?
え、ってことはもうおわ
Eh, does that mean it's ov—
ちょっと待って！
Wait a minute!
え、でもポルカが、待って、ポルカが追いついてない！
Eh, but Polka hasn't caught up!
あなたの上手にポルカが追いついていない！
Polka hasn't kept up with you!
最初だって、下がるんやろ？
At first, you go down, right?
下がるのがなんかなくな...な、え、もう上がっちゃってるじゃん！
Going down, it disappeared— wait, it already went up!
大きくまったね、ザインくんも。すごいね、大きくなったね！
You got big, Zain-kun too. Amazing, you got big!
あー、なるほどね。あの、諸々の諸般の事情により錆作ろ。
Ah, I see. Due to various circumstances, let's make the chorus.
錆だけめっちゃクオリティを上げて、あとで動画で、あの、前の、前の部分を作ればいいじゃん！いいじゃん！
Just make the chorus super high quality, and then make the earlier part in a video later! That's fine!
錆だけじゃ、しょ、しょうけ、いいんじゃないの？
Just the chorus, isn't that fine?
ええと、ちょっと待って、はい、歌手に聞いて、帰ってきて。
Um, wait, yes, ask the singer, come back.
か、歌手、歌手さ、ちょっと作詞だよって言ってさ、一緒に手伝ってくれるって言ったじゃん！
You said it was lyric-writing and that you'd help together!
一緒に手伝ってくれるって言ったじゃん、なんでそこで裏切るの？
You said you'd help together, why are you betraying me?
さっきさ、ほら、なんとかのアーチとか、虹がうんちゃらとか、
Earlier, look, something's arch, or rainbows, etc.,
あれ？え？だって、え？
Huh? Eh? But, eh?
かぶったなしじゃない。え？さあさあさあ、なんとかの虹の光、光が夢で、あれ？
It wasn't covered? Now now now, the light of some rainbow...
えっと...ポルカも変えとけばよかった。
Umm... I should've changed Polka too.
じゃあ 虹の 虹のアーチ
Well, a rainbow... a rainbow arch...
虹が 虹がかかるステージで
On a stage where a rainbow... where a rainbow arches...
虹がかかるステージで
On a stage where a rainbow arches,
虹が 虹 虹の 虹の
A rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow,
虹の 虹の 虹 虹 きらめくステージで
Rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, on a sparkling stage!
虹きらめくステージで
On a rainbow-sparkling stage,
笑顔を見せて
Show me your smile.
虹が 虹が かかったステージで
On a stage where a rainbow... where a rainbow arched,
笑顔を見せて
Show me your smile.
今頑張ってるね 今頑張って動かしてんだよ これでも このちっちゃいおててでね
You're working hard now, moving it even with these tiny hands.
虹が 虹の 虹の 虹がかかるステージで
A rainbow, rainbow, rainbow, on a stage where a rainbow arches,
虹がかかるステージで
On a stage where a rainbow arches,
笑顔を 笑顔を...
Show your smile... show your smile...
笑顔を見せるよ 飛び切りの笑顔を見せるよ
I'll show you an extraordinary smile!
スマイル キラめく笑顔を見せるよ キラキラの笑顔を見せるよ
Smile... sparkling, I'll show you a glittering smile!
笑顔を咲かせるよ 海の苦しみだねそれは 海の苦しみなんだよ
I'll make a smile bloom. That's the sea's suffering, huh? It's the sea's suffering!
今一緒に頑張ってるからさ 笑顔を...
Since we're working hard together now, a smile...
まあそういうのは置いといて これね、何に？ コンペ前の曲だから、ちょっと待っといてな。
Leaving that aside, umm, this is... what? It's a song before the competition, so wait a minute.
満天の笑顔を上げる 虹がかかるステージで 満天の笑顔を上げる
Raising a sky-full smile! On a stage where a rainbow arches, raising a sky-full smile!
虹がかかるステージで 満天の笑顔を上げる
On a stage where a rainbow arches, raising a sky-full smile!
なんとかのカンとか... なんとかのカンとか
Somehow's kan'toka... somehow's kan'toka...
走り出すよ 急に走りたがり 走り出すよ
I'll start running! Suddenly wanting to run, I'll start running,
どんな時でも
No matter what time it is,
ヤ号が出てこない今頭の中に。すごい頭の中にヤ号が出てくる。
I can't think of the 'ya-word' in my head right now. It keeps popping up.
生まるな、生まるな！大丈夫か？元気出して
Don't be born! Are you okay? Cheer up!
走り出すよ 2年目もまたね！なるほどね！
I'll start running! Year 2 as well! I see!
それが感情のジェットコースター フリーフォールじゃないどっちかっていうと
That's an emotional roller coaster—not quite a free fall, rather...
それが感情のジェットこ... なんか「感情って」なんか ゴツくない？
That's an emotional jet co... isn't 'emotion' a bit rugged?
ジェットコースターはいいんだけど 気圧圧にも負けずにジェットコースター
Jet coasters are fine, but without yielding to air pressure, how about a jet coaster?
テンションジェットコースター？ いいね！ あ、キミが来た！
Tension jet coaster? Sounds good! Ah, you came!
じゃあ、フルで歌えばいいんじゃね？ 歌うぞ！
Well, shouldn't I just sing it in full? I'm gonna sing!
虹がかかるステージで 満天の笑顔を上げる... 感情のジェットコースター
On a stage where a rainbow arches, raising a sky-full smile... Emotional roller coaster
走り出したもと止まらない オーバーボルカ... 頑張るよみんなにとどけと この気持ち伝えたい
Running out, unstoppable! Over Polka... I'll do my best to deliver it to everyone, I want to convey this feeling!
動画にするよ
We're making a video out of this.
これ動画にするから。
We're making a video out of this, you see.
でもテープのデモデモデモテープでした。
But it turned out to be a demo tape!
いや、頑張ったよ。
Man, we did our best.
頑張ったよ、おれたち。
We really did our best, didn't we?
このさん、ありがとう！ありがとうだな！
Kono-san, thank you! Thank you so much!
いや、頑張りました！満点！
Man, we did great! Perfect score!
というわけで！
So anyway!
こちら一周年のお歌を作ろう。まあ、タイトルもちょっと後で考えるとして、まあ今後に行きたいということで、そのコーナーでした。ありがとうございました！
Let's create a 1st anniversary song. We'll think of a title later, but as a segment looking forward to the future... thank you very much!
こねさん今日はありがとう、ほたるの光
Kono-san, thank you for today...
雑に吐けちまった。一番今日頑張ってたのに。
I botched it so casually, even though I worked hardest today!
ええと、はい、というわけで、ちょっと自分で積っちまった。
Um, yes, so... I messed up on my own.
はい、ここで何と何と、何と何と何と何と何と何となくまとめつつ告知したいと思いますので、
Yes, here I'd like to make some announcements while summarizing things somewhat...
ポルカの息がね、あ、いい感じ。告知の曲っぽいの流れ出してきたな。
Polka's breathing is... oh, nice. It's starting to sound like an announcement track.
というわけで尾丸ポルカ一周年配信どうでしたか？
So how was Omaru Polka's 1st anniversary stream?
はい、まだまだ話すけど尾丸ポルカ一周年でつぶやいてってね！
Yes, keep tweeting about Omaru Polka's 1st anniversary!
いやね、もうコメントも拾う余裕もないので、じゃあここでいきなり、ですか... お知らせです！
Yeah, well, I don't even have time to check comments, so now... here it is, an announcement!
はい、ドン！尾丸ポルカ活動一周年！こちら8月16日、このあと9時からブースにて販売させていただきます！お楽しみにー！
Tada! Omaru Polka's 1st anniversary! Starting August 16th, right after this at 9 PM, they will be on sale at the booth! Look forward to it!
はい、こちら、ね、なんとなんと、まあ素晴らしい、素晴らしいことに変わりないんだけどさ、すごいよろ、すごいよろ。今回はなんと、ええとちょっとね、またママから違って、赤木先生にイラストをお願いしております。まあ、なんだって要はみてをこれ、はい、じゃあ続きのドン、こちら！
Yes, this... you know, no matter what, it's amazing. This time, unlike before, we asked Akamoku-sensei to draw the illustrations. Well, anyway, look at this! Yes, now for the next part, tada! Here!
はい、ポルカがいない、これ慣れてなさすぎる。はい、ポルカおるよ等身大タペストリーというのはですね、まあ、存在感ですね。
Yes, Polka isn't here—I'm too unaccustomed to this. Yes, the "Polka Oru yo Life-Sized Tapestry" is, well... it has such presence.
あのね、ママにはまた違った色々なことを頼んでいるので、赤木先生にすげえ存在感のあるポルカくださいていうことで、もうこれ153cmのポルカがお前の、お前のお家に行くよっていう感じで。なんでポルカ春物がめっちゃ好きなんだろね。
You see, we asked Mama for various different things, and we asked Akamoku-sensei for a Polka with incredible presence, so a 153cm Polka will come to your house! Why does Polka love spring items so much, I wonder?
あの、クローゼットとかガって開けたらさ、「ポルカおるよ」「うわ、ポルカおったわ」みたいなのにしたらいいんじゃない？使い方が的には。
If you open your closet or something and go, "Polka's here!" "Whoa, Polka's here!", something like that–usage-wise.
まあ、これね、ポルカ見たの、全面とりあえず3個くらい部屋に貼ってみたけどさ、うーん、うーん、賑やか。一気に家族が増えたって感じになっちゃって、ちょっと。また抱き枕とかとは全然違った感じになるけど、しかもめちゃ触り心地がよかった！
Well, I tried putting up about three full-face Polkas around my room, and... yeah, bustling. It felt like my family suddenly grew, so... it's a totally different vibe from a dakimakura or anything, but plus, it felt super nice to touch!
というわけで続いては、こちら！はい、みんな、お待たせ！座員くんぬいぐるみだよ！耳の再現度ヤバすぎ！わろた。このもさもさ、そして一番のこだわりは最後までグッズの方とお話ししたこの切り抜きのハートです！
So next is this! Yes, everyone, thanks for waiting! It's the Zaiin-kun plushie! The ear accuracy is insane! Lol. This fluffy texture, and the ultimate detail we discussed with the merch team until the end is this cutout heart!
ハートの部分がね、ちゃんと縁取りされてるから、あの、なんとかじょうぶ、うん、なんとかじょうぶ。ね、みんなもこうやって口のないものになってしまおうということで、物言わぬ座員くんになってしまうわけですよ。こちらは何個あってもいいね。
The heart part has proper edging, so it's, um, pretty sturdy. Yeah, pretty sturdy. Right, everyone should become faceless like this too, turning into speechless Zaiin-kun. You can never have too many of these.
ね、根っこ とね、あの、サイズがいい感じだった。サイズ機能調べた感じ。
The roots and size felt just right. Based on checking the size specs.
はい、そしてフルセットの特典は、尾丸ポルカからの複製手紙、お手紙！手紙を手紙？いや、手書きを手紙や。手書きのお手紙です！
Yes, and the full set bonus is a replicated letter, a letter from Omaru Polka! A letter from a letter? No, a handwritten letter. It's a handwritten letter!
いや、ポストカードをさっきね、Twitterで「いやポストカードあるんだったら学ぶぢ買わなあかんな」みたいな人見てて、「どうしようポストカードねえわ」って思いながら、ただお手紙、ポルカ好きなんだよね。
Yeah, I saw someone on Twitter earlier saying, "If there's a postcard, I gotta buy the merch bundle," and I was thinking, "What should I do, there's no postcard," but I love writing letters.
万年筆で書くのがすごい好きだから、ぜひこれは受け取ってほしいです。そして記念ボイスはちょっと変わった趣向のね、なんかいろんなボイスになってるから、それもまたページ、ブースのページで見てください。色々概要欄とかにこのあと、なんだこれ回転しとるわ。乗せたりするよ。
I really love writing with a fountain pen, so I definitely want you to receive this. And the commemorative voice packs have a slightly unique twist with various voices, so please check those out on the Booth page. We'll post them in the description later... wait, it's spinning.
よしチェックやで！というわけで、ありがとうございました！
Check it out! So, thank you very much!
こんな感じで、だいだいだ、だいだい大満足だと思います。いやあ、そうですね数量ね。いつもの戦争が大変だとか言ってる人たち、焦らず焦らず。焦らない焦らない。ポルカは逃げないよ。ポルカはここに居るよ。ポルカおるよ！はい、ポルカおるよタペストリーということで、あ、急ですがそろそろお別れです。
Like this, I think you'll be super, super, super satisfied. Yeah, well, quantities, you know. For those who always say "the merch wars are tough," don't panic, don't panic. Don't rush, don't rush. Polka isn't running away. Polka is right here. Polka is here! Yes, the "Polka is here tapestry"–anyway, it's almost time to say goodbye.
というわけでね、ポルカ一周年に過ぎ去ってまいりました。
And so, Omaru Polka's 1st anniversary has quickly flown by.
この後は、えーと、IDの子たちが新衣装もあるし大変なんだよー！
After this, um, the ID girls have new outfits too, so it's a lot of work!
悲しいですが、もうそろそろお別れの時間です。
It's sad, but it's almost time to say goodbye.
悲しいですが、そろそろお別れの時間です。
元気なBGMが今日も…（笑）
Lively BGM again today... (laughs)
お、えっ、なんか、時差がある。ポルカと、なんか、場内のザインくんスタッフと…
Oh, wait, there's a time lag. Between Polka and, like, Zain-kun and the staff in the venue...
えー、今日は、え、それだけじゃないぞ！この後終わってから、ねぽらぼの動画も上がっちゃうんだぞ！
Uh, today, uh, that's not all! After this ends, a Nepolabo video is going up too!
そっちは15分からチェックしてね！今はまだシルエットになってるけど、まあ楽しみにしといてくんないし！
Check that out from 15 minutes! Right now it's still a silhouette, but look forward to it!
でも、でもそのあと、なぜか、半から、謎の「ぽ」という動画が上がっているわけですが、こちら、予想がついている方は予想がついていて、予想がついてない方はついてなくて、おまるポルカはポルカです。
And then, for some reason, a mysterious video called 'Po' goes up at half-past. Those who guessed it guessed it, those who didn't didn't, and Omaru Polka is Polka.
というわけで、初披露の、オリジナル曲を、みんなに聞いてもらいたいと思います！
And so, I want everyone to listen to my very first original song!
ポルカね、これね、えっと、言い訳から入らせて。BPM333なんだ。
Polka, you see, um, let me start with an excuse. The BPM is 333.
ちょっとポルカ歌えないからさ、ちょっとDJブース、カモン！
Polka can't sing it, so DJ booth, come on!
そういうわけさ。ちょっとね、ポルカが盛り上げながら、みんなにこの曲の楽しさを知ってもらうため、そう、オリジナルの曲を、えっと、やっちゃいますよ！
That's how it is. So that Polka can hype it up and let everyone know how fun this song is, yeah, we're gonna do my original song!
というわけで、準備はいいかな？テンションぶち上げ音圧マックス音量最大、ギューイン！聞いてください！オリジナル曲、ぽ！
So, are you ready? Turn up your tension, max sound pressure, max volume, guh-in! Listen to it! My original song, Po!
ぽぽぽぽぽぽぽぽ
Po-po-po-po-po-po-po-po
やっほー！ポルカだよ～
Yahoo! It's Polka~
って、なんか声が変じゃない？
Wait, doesn't my voice sound weird?
あー、あー、聞こえますか～？
Ah, ah, can you hear me~?
おーーーい、だめか
Heyyy, is this no good?
このままずっとぽで生活するのか？
Am I gonna live life as 'po' forever?
やだな～
No way~
なんかあっちにあるぞ？よくわかんないけど、とりあえず行ってみよ～
There's something over there? I don't really get it, but let's go check it out~
ぽぽぽぽぽぽぽぽ
Po-po-po-po-po-po-po-po
なんか怖いとこに出たぞ
I ended up in some scary place
暗いし寒いし嫌だな～
It's dark and cold, I hate this~
うーん、どっかなぁ、今度はあっちに行ってみよ～
Hmm, I wonder where, let's try going that way this time~
ぽぽぽぽぽぽぽぽ
Po-po-po-po-po-po-po-po
うわぁ、絶対道間違ったわ…
Whoa, I definitely took the wrong path...
落ちたら死ぬやん
If I fall I'll die
なんかすげー臭いし、悪い夢なら覚めてくれ～
It smells terrible, wake me up from this bad dream~
ん？なんか音が聞こえる？
Hm? Do I hear some sound?
うわぁ！
Whoa!
なんかやっぱりこっち来る！にげろにげろ！
It's coming this way after all! Run, run!
にげろー！
Run away!
ぽぽぽぽぽぽぽぽ
Po-po-po-po-po-po-po-po
ありがとう！ぽぽぽぽぽぽぽ！
Thank you! Po-po-po-po-po-po-po!
このあと、12時からこちらが曲配信するよっていうのをスタッフさんに出してっていうの忘れてた！
I forgot to tell the staff to put out that the song will be streaming from 12 o'clock!
ぽぽぽぽぽぽぽ… ぽー！
Po-po-po-po-po-po... Po!
ぽー！ちねん！
Po! Chinen!
「ねぇねぇ、なんで昨日既読してくれないの？」
"Hey, hey, why didn't you read my message yesterday?"
「あ〜寝てたわ笑 ごめんごめん笑」
"Ah~ I was sleeping lol. Sorry, sorry lol."
「ねぇねぇ」
"Hey, hey..."
「コイツとイチャイチャリポしてんのなんなん？」
"What's up with you being all cozy and replying to this guy?"
「あ〜笑」
"Ah~ lol"
「最近仲良くしてるネッ友だけど？笑」
"We're just internet friends we've been getting along with, you know? lol"
「舐めてんの？」
"Are you messing with me?"
「てめぇめぇだよ」
"You're one to talk."
譲れないプライド
Unyielding pride,
何度目のcry?
how many times must I cry?
もう寸前の「Like」
A "Like" is right on the verge—
お前の全部暴いて破壊
I'll expose and destroy all of you.